software engineering radio episode 15
the future of enterprise Java
[Music]
so in this episode ever hopped and
myself will talk about the future of
enterprise Java Enterprise Java is
probably the biggest market area in
which Java has been adopted there is of
course the standard edition for the
client and there is j2me for various
kinds of mobile devices but I think the
biggest impact Java has had or and still
has is in the enterprise area therefore
the discussion about the future of
enterprise Java and its current state is
probably an interesting discussion
before we actually discuss the future of
enterprise Java let's first try to come
up with a definition or some kind of
description what Enterprise Java
actually is so my definition would be
enterprise Java is supplying Java to
problems for enterprise mission critical
software and in these areas you usually
have to have support for a lot of
different things for example a remote
communication which is offered by h-e-b
or web services as an Cronus
communication which is offered by GM s
legacy integration integration of whole
systems with Tracy a web which is
usually supported by circuits and some
web frameworks transactions two-phase
commit all these nice things that Tracy
offers management using jmx and also
deployment administration monitoring and
so on which is a very important part for
application service in general the
important point is that this is much
more than just your average web
application this can be done as well
using the toolset of enterprise Java but
we are talking about real enterprise
applications here which means stuff that
is otherwise only doable with COBOL
transaction managers and such so web
applications can of course also be done
using Enterprise Java but it's not
really the focus and I believe this is
one of the arrows in your state's book
beyond Java because he focuses in my
opinion too much on claiming that Java
is bad for putting databases into the
web and this is just not what Enterprise
Java is intended to be and be useful I
recently took a more-or-less closer look
at Ruby on Rails and I'm not planning on
following the hype here and saying that
rails is so much
than Java for this and that but one has
to admit that if you look at the
programming model that rails provides
that this really much nicer than all the
stuff you see in the Java world for
doing web development so it's really
important to distinguish web development
where you put a couple of database
tables on line with a nice design maybe
even scale ibly and comparing that to
mission-critical back-end enterprise
applications and the j2ee standard or
java enterprise standard is more
intended for that area so and I think
it's really important to make that clear
and the other important point is that
there are not so many alternatives it's
something that you can do with Java
probably with net and that's it and old
school stuff like COBOL and so on
talking about Ruby on Rails there are
several web frameworks on the Java side
I think there are some approaches that
can at least compete with Ruby on Rails
such as Grails for groovy which is more
or less inspired by Ruby on Rails there
are approaches that give you a project
skeleton using hibernate spring or
another choice of frameworks like a fuse
or Equinox those are more less project
skeletons the point is especially those
kind of projects they can be done
without eg be without JMS without DMX
without JCA so all of those interesting
enterprise Java technologies are just
not important for this kind of
application you're saying that the
landscape is changing on this Web area
so it basically that the java world
accepted the challenge that PHP and and
Ruby on Rails set so that things are
going to come up with a better
programming model in the future for
simple web applications I think that's
quite obvious I mean simplification is
one of the goals of Java 5 something
that is there with with grades and so on
so I think that's quite obvious but on
the other hand you have to say that a
lot of web applications probably even
the majority haven't been done with Java
but rather with PHP Perl and so on so
the question is whether Ruby on Rails is
really competiting against Java or
rather against PHP and so on so that's
just an open question I mean the as you
pointed out it's very very good
framework for doing web development but
this is not what we are going to focus
on in this
especially okay something you already
mentioned Thor not explicitly we talked
about the term programming model and we
also I think mentioned the word
infrastructure once or twice yeah I
think you have something to say on that
one the important part is in my opinion
to a separate programming model from
infrastructure the definition of an
infrastructure to me is is something
that manages connection threads
resources and so on in Java EE this is
usually a container an application
server with certain components that live
inside this application server even
though this is ubiquitous in Java EE it
is not a concept by itself meaning that
there is no term in Java EE that says
okay there is a general container and
software containers just a special
version of this container slept row
using gem X as a means of providing
something like this so Jay makes
microkernel application service I mean
we already thought of discussing this
topic in our previous episode on
components and then how component
technologies changed from EJB one point
x2 maybe things like spring and you say
that we should consciously distinguish
between the programming model and the
infrastructure and basically to repeat
from what we said back then let the
infrastructure be done by the big
vendors and let the programming model be
defined by those who have to use it
which is the programmers which is
probably the open source community just
to sum up so the the programming model
it defines how you actually write the
software and I think one of the more
impressing parts where this is obvious
is for web application frameworks so in
the Java area there is struts JSF JSP
velocity free mark spring MVC web work
and so on and so on and those are all
very different programming models but
they all are based on the same
infrastructure circuits so that means
that any infrastructure that provides
surf lots any application server can run
any of those frameworks and this
illustrates this point I think quite
good so enterprise Java means that you
have to use Java application service as
an infrastructure and something with
Java as a programming model and even
there you could come up with a lot of
different things
groovy module
purchase spring whatever so more or less
the infrastructure is like an operating
system and it's quite obvious that you
can run perl applications see
applications Java applications and so on
on an operating system like Linux or Mac
OS 10 or whatever so with this you're
not suggesting to run C on the JVM and
an application server rather you're
saying that there is this standardized
well-defined infrastructure which is the
same thing as the operating system in
one level lower and then you should
basically allow people to define their
own languages acha programming models so
that for whatever task they have to
accomplish they can use suitable
programming models and maybe what you're
also saying is that the standardization
process is j-stars and stuff they should
focus on standardizing the
infrastructure and the vendors should
try to make their systems fast and
stable and well manageable and should
don't care about the program model so
much the next thing to answer is
probably why if the future of interest
Java is an important question I mean why
should you spend a whole podcast episode
talking about this and why should you
spend the time listening to us I think
the main reason is that enterprise is
the strong point of Java a lot of
companies have strategic commitments to
Java and those companies include large
players like Oracle Sun IBM B ASAP and
the move to Java is still very strong
there meaning that it's still the case
that new people come about and also one
approach Java you're saying although
some of the loud and noisy gurus are
going away to some cooler languages the
folks with the money are still moving
towards Java and not away from it that's
at least what I see and bake a few weeks
ago I read a German newspaper called
computer Sarang and there were two or
three articles on one page saying okay
so this is the newest strategy of our
company in terms of software and we are
moving towards Java and we are doing
this and that with Java and this is a
magazine that is rather read by managers
than by technical people so one of the
things that has always been received
critically by the developer community in
j2ee is ejbs Enterprise Java
beans one could maybe even argue that
some of the bad reputation that j2ee has
in some circles is actually the bad
reputation of EJB and not the better
reputation of j2e in general I think
it's fair that we take a closer look at
each a be and answer the question of
first of all what is EJB and second how
bad is it really I think that's quite an
important point to say that it should be
is really complex and this kind of
spreads out towards all of j2ee because
there are even pull books that talk
about how bad it should be is like
bitter Jimmy for example and there are
other books that even take the next step
and say okay so you shouldn't use HB and
this is the way to go
like really development without HB for
example so how bad is it to be really
basically HB is from 1998 this is an
important part because in a way it
should be is an enhancement and it's an
enhancement compared to Aqaba it
simplified some of the kaabah
approaching by giving you an all-in-one
component type while in Kaabah you have
to decide on every aspect of the
component yourself like lifecycle
security transactions and so on in it
should be this all done automatically
this is also something that we talked
about probably in the component patterns
episode and some techniques like putting
for example quite a good idea back then
because of the quality of the JVM stem
so the important part here is HP was
step forward when it originally appeared
on the scene and that was 1998
so the question is how we look at it
should be nowadays also there is another
ancestor to each JB and that's the
classical transaction monitor such as
tuxedo or kicks I guess is also one so
and comparing the programming model of
EJB to tuxedo for example and NBA's mm3
and stuff I mean I haven't ever worked
with those things but what I heard and
what I saw
EJ B was an improvement so it's really I
think important to see in the historical
context it's already historical from the
point of view of 2006 I guess so in
nowadays each B is received to be just
too complex and it means for example I
just plain wrong and taking a look at it
should be three you can clearly see this
and security was also not good
fit for most of the challenges and real
projects for example it was just raw
based and it was not data dependent so
you couldn't say ok the customer can
only see its own account this couldn't
be done with security and also I think
one of the biggest problems is that each
B doesn't make the right way
the easiest way so if you do it should
be in a naive way the code is not
independent from the technology it's not
easy testable so you have to do a lot of
interesting things to get this and this
is really a big drawback of the
programming model it means that if you
do it the way it's most easy you end up
with a bad system and I think one could
argue that this is a consequence of the
fact that back then people didn't
distinguish between programming model
and infrastructure so you basically have
to work the raw iron me you have to work
directly on the infrastructure without
having a standardized nicer programming
model would you agree I believe the real
problem is that some of the things that
are now looking so bad just haven't been
on the landscape when et was originally
done I mean testing has been one of the
large things that XP extreme programming
brought into the scene and this hasn't
been so much around when egb was
originally done and in also believe this
is not the real problem I think the real
problem is that starting with an
improvement over Kaba is not the worst
way to start a standard the problem is
the slow and in appropriate improvements
that were made for each beam so for
example HB 3 takes two years from public
draft to finalization for example
security is still not improved and if
each eb was constantly improved things
would be quite different right now and
this is the real problem it's not
something that is evolving fastly or
it's just something that every few years
somebody looks over it and trusts
improving in a certain way so you're
saying back then when it came out it was
ok and if the EJB standard had been able
to adopt to the increasing understanding
of how things should be if that hadn't
taken as long as it had taken then
things would be better today so EJB
you mentioned already is it better is it
good I mean is it what we all wanted
well first of all the question is why
should you send it as a programming
model so in a way that's asking what's
the point anyway because I think
important is just to senators the
interface to the application server and
that's it but you could argue that it's
even maybe more important to standardize
the programming model I mean I write
programs so I want to run this kind of
program on all kinds of systems so why
wouldn't you want to standardize the
programming model because if you send to
us the infrastructure in a proper way
then you can still run it on every
platform without changing the code and
so you don't get the problem of no
portability but you get the freedom of
choosing a programming model that fits
your needs so instead of taking your
program and running it on a different
application server you would take your
program plus your programming model
framework and run that one exactly
that's the point the other questions why
should I care I mean how many people are
supporting e 2 B 3 in my opinion there
are three big players in the Java EE
world so that stray boss drevis is quite
in favor for you B 3 and is strongly
supporting it there is ba ba actually
doesn't care because they support each B
3 as much as they support spring and
they also trying to move into the market
of enterprise operating systems they're
more focusing on stability easy
administration and so on then on the
programming model which is in my opinion
quite a smart move and I'm not sure
about how IBM is behaving so comparing
the situation now from what it was like
when it should be 2 came around the Java
EE world is not so uniform anymore so
it's not that everybody says ok so it
should be the new version is the way to
go it's rather that there are some
people that work in favor of it and
other people that where you can't really
be sure so in a strategic way it's an
open Chris Froome at HP 3 is so
important so that's the strategic answer
the last answer is probably the
technical answer I think the real
benefit is the standardized java
persistence api and there are already a
lot of products around and companies
like Oracle for example to a law to
market this approach and technically
this is not such a big improvement
this could also have been reached by
making trade you're part of Hawaii and
it's also something that can be
sanitized in a sensible way because we
know how to do object relational mapping
in a proper way because we've done that
for like I don't know 10 15 20 years or
so so it's something that we know how to
deal with I've stopped counting but
there is a CMP 1.0 CMP 1.1 CMP 2.0
hibernate okay that's not a standard
then there is 2.1 CMP there is cheerio
probably 1 2 & 3
now there's another Java persistence
mapping is it really that complicated
and it's the new EJB 3 per systems or
whatever it's officially called is it
good I mean I heard that it's basically
hibernate with a couple of different
names it's good because it ends the
persistence wall that we've been seeing
with Dre do J do 2 and it should be 3m
so I think in this regard it's really a
good thing and I think it's also a
sensible standard because it's a pointed
out there's a lot of experience out
there and a lot of really experienced
people have been participating in
standardizing this and hibernate as you
mention is one of the best examples for
such a good and well working approach to
earth stroke resistance so you're saying
that each epi is not going to be as
dominant as it has been from my point of
view EJB has always been good for
certain problems if you have distributed
transactions and it must be highly
scalable and that stuff then each EBS
hasn't ever been a bad thing I mean
forget entity beans but the rest wasn't
too bad so you're saying basically that
for those things each a B will probably
continue to be a good choice but for all
those 80% other applications that don't
have these highly sophisticated
requirements there are better
programming models and if that's what
you're saying then what are those are
the programming models what's on the
horizon you want to make me say spring
one of the lessons to learn here is a
business core need not necessarily be
done with HP and that was one of the
major wrong judgments that were made you
have Java EE and HP is the one to use
for business logic and servlets are used
for the web city and so on and that's
just not how it must be done it can be
done this way it might make sense
other thing is that in certain areas
such as security there's still new
improvement so it's not necessarily true
that in those highly scalable
environments and it should be is really
the obvious choice it's also that still
drawbacks the other lesson to learn in
my opinion is even though something is a
standard it does not necessarily mean
that this is the best thing to have and
in the case of egb it's quite obvious
talking about it should be two and one
it's quite obvious now that even though
it was a standard it's an approach that
has been really really arguable so the
lessons to learn here even though
something is a standard it doesn't
necessarily mean that it's really
something that you must use that fits
all your needs and is really really
great to use so we should go on away
from the EJB topic and servlets are
probably something that has really been
successful servlets are used as the
backend for web services basically for
an infrastructure they're used as a
package for web applications and they're
not the programming model anymore
so here this transition from programming
model to infrastructure has already been
done implicitly or explicitly I don't
know if somebody decided that but their
other programming models are available
so maybe let's take a look at the web
tier then in the web tier I think there
is the biggest freedom of choice because
there are just so many web frameworks
around the other important thing to
notice here is and that's again related
to standards struts is a huge success
story for a non standardized
open-source framework it means that
there was an issue that was not taken by
standard and that was trusting over by
struts and this was widely adopted and
it has widespread support now so this is
an area where you can see that a non
sanitized open source frameworks can
really be something that works in
practice and is really really usable and
good and also become sort of a de-facto
standard while on the other hand you can
see GB and that's a real standard but
it's not so usable the other interesting
part looking back
RJ's feels really a good idea originally
when they came on the scene if they were
at least I thought quite a good idea
because
you don't have to ride swords anymore
and you don't have to write this out
print line my HTML code but rather have
an HTML site with embedded Java nowadays
there are two drawbacks in my opinion
one drawback is that you have to have
this compile step that takes the JSP
does some good code generation finally
generates bytecode from that with Java
compiler for example and the other
problem is that this programming model
allows the embedding of code and logic
inside a presentation layer which is
obviously not really a good idea so
looking back today's peas are probably
not such a good idea anymore I mean if
they're used correctly like if you just
basically use tag libraries and these
kinds of things then there probably
aren't too bad and also there is a lot
of competition so there is for example
velocity or free market so the
competition kind of levels those
problems so there are other approaches
these approaches are probably going to
work better for me and I can take those
so that's another advantage a question
to me is is the multitude of solutions a
problem so there are a lot of different
web frameworks out there and it's
probably becoming hard to choose the
right one and I'm also quite fascinated
by the large amount of interests in
spring MVC I give a lot of spring
workshops and I'm quite surprised that
people are really interested in this
even though I thought that the main
point for spring a dependency injection
AOP and the API abstraction for Java EE
and Java and so on so that's something
that puzzles me but isn't that the same
thing again that most people when they
think about enterprise think about web
and then spring MVC is obviously a
solution that's mainly used for web
development yeah probably I mean it's
something that I still have to find out
why this is so important for them
probably it's because they are looking
for a different solution for web
development and the other question to
ask there is whether the best monastry
winning so is the competition really
open I think for example JSF has an
advantage because it's a standard so
it's something that has an advantage
because it has more support and the
alternative that JSF is probably
becoming is this a one solution fits all
approach that don't net for example he
uses with asp.net so you're saying that
JSF is going to be important JSF is
going to be a major standard yeah I mean
it's going to be important just because
it's it's a standard that's for sure it
is and judging from the true support at
least it's something that a lot of
people seem to have been waiting for so
I think also in this regard it's going
to be quite important I'm not sure
whether JSF is such a good idea in
technical terms it's just an open
question one thing that's obvious is
that you can't use it without tools
I mean you shouldn't even try to do that
by just coding and that's probably also
one of the philosophical differences to
things like Ruby on Rails because rail
says you can do everything by a coding
and you have this convention over
configuration thing and in in JSF you
don't have that you have to configure
everything five times but if you do that
with suitable tools that's not a problem
so JSF is obviously a framework that's
made for tools that was my impression
and I think focusing on the development
of user interfaces when designing a tool
is not the best approach because the
complexity is almost always about the
code itself the logic and so on and
focusing on doing user interface
development can easily lead to a mass
like you have it in Visual Basic for
example since we're already discussing
about the web it's probably also a good
thing to take a last look at the battle
for the web because this is the area
where you can see the most competition
as we said before rails trails Grails
whatever other frameworks there are so
those questions will Java prevail as a
framework for doing the classical web
applications
I believe that Sonoma question and I
think crusade in Buren Java did quite a
good job and in pointing out that there
are other approaches like seaside for
example squeek seaside or Ruby on Rails
that are really really good in this area
so you're talking about continuations
yeah I mean seaside is doing this it's
quite an interesting thing and also the
huge success story about Joe who's shops
is obviously based on this Yahoo shops
has been done with the continuation
framework and was later on bought by Joe
the success has largely been due to
being able to
quickly come up with new features if the
competition has those features
continuations are basically using a way
of giving the client the whole execution
context of the application and later on
the ability to continue a at precisely
this point this is quite powerful
because that way you can write a linear
program with the steps of your
application and every time you need some
user input the computation is just
suspended and the user input is taken
from the user and then it continues so
it's quite an easy model so to make that
clear if today you're implementing a web
application then what you're basically
doing is you're coding a state machine
you receive certain events which is the
HTTP requests from your client you
basically check where in the workflow
you are and then you do something you
send out an action and then you're
passively again waiting for the next
event to come in if you want to model
the page flow then state machines are
good things to do that because you're
basically implementing a state machine
and what continuations allow you to do
is you basically you write a program and
if you go back like 25 years till the
time when you've been programming for
ms-dos if you wanted to know something
from the user
you basically wrote console dot readline
please insert your age and then you
basically blocked and you wait it until
the guy entered 35 and pressed enter and
then in the next line of code you used
the return value of this read line stuff
and continue so you have a linear
program flow so basically when you're
waiting for the user to input something
you kind of step out and block the
program until the user inputs hits value
and you can do the same thing with
continuations for the web
you basically output a message which in
this case is obviously an HTML page in
some way and then you just go on and
work with the results there and the
framework makes sure that the
computation is suspended the user is
being sent the HTML page they enter
whatever data they have to enter it's
returned and then the computation
transparently continues at the point
where it stopped before it has the whole
contacts the whole stack all variables
but also the values that the guy entered
into the page and this allows for a
really really really
nice and simple programming model the
traditional model of course is
model-view-controller base and also
there there are good approaches like
ljubljana it's for example i think in
the java space there are at least some
competition I'm actually not aware of
anything like continuations in Java
because that's hard to do I'm not a
hundred percent sure but there is
something called rife and I think this
is a continuation project for Java and I
also think but I'm also not 100% sure is
that Kevin King in his new seem
framework is also working on integrating
continuations I'm not sure whether the
programming model will be exactly the
same as the continuations we know from
seaside or something but the idea
certainly perpetuates into Java and is
being adopted it's not clear yet in
which way if anybody of our listeners
know something about that we'll be
interested in learning about that I
think one thing you can learn from
Renault yets is that it's good to have
some kind of project skeleton and to
generate this this can be done with
equinox web fuse which are project
skeletons that also allow you flexible
integrations of different frameworks so
you have the choice of persistence
framework for example there is the
trails framework that tries to port the
ideas of Ruby on Rails to tapestry
spring and it's also using a generator
based approach what you are still
lacking is the power of dynamically
typed language and this is done with
Grails that uses groovy and framework to
get the same ideas as Ruby on Rails but
still I mean those things are inspired
by Ruby on Rails but the original idea
is still Ruby on Rails so in a way this
illustrates that there are other
programming models using the same
infrastructure that have more power and
allow you to run on this highly
optimized widely available and well
understood infrastructure okay next
topic web services this have had kind of
a slow start in j2ee
but in the meantime I think they've been
adopted so anything to say they're using
J's r18 one it's now becoming much more
easy to do them and also standardized
and the interesting part is that remote
coming
that now takes place by using servlets
HTTP and web services means that each
bees become even more pointless because
as flexible highly scalable
infrastructure and can now be offered by
Web Services again also there are a lot
of different implementations as access
Xfire and every application - its own
implementation of web services and it's
an easy scalable way with good
inoperability
there is also a choice of more
lightweight protocols like burlap or
Hessian there are even easier to use but
they are not standardized and in this
area it's important to have a standard
because if you have standard like web
services you can be pretty sure that
interoperability works that you can use
it cross-platform and so on and that's
probably one of the weaker sides of
fashion enveloped that there is no
interface definition language and this
way it's not easy to say okay so here's
the file and this describes my service
and please use it from whatever language
you want this is not something that you
can implement here but it's another way
of doing easy scalable and fault
tolerant services without using
something like an application server
ubian so therefore these web services
and HTTP base node protocols add even
more value to suffereth containers so I
think this concludes our discussion
about the high visibility features of
j2ee which is basically EJB and web
based stuff let's take a brief look at
some of the other stuff the reason why
we should only probably take a brief
look is because it's kind of undoubted
that those things are actually good if
you look at JCA the Java connector API
or the Java transaction API and also the
management infrastructure then I think
people agree that this is actually the
foundation of real enterprise systems
transaction legacy integration and
manageability and these things probably
don't have too much competition on the
market so in that area
I think j2e is really still up to date
and quite a good thing so what do you
think about that aspect the interesting
part is that a framework such as spring
can make the usage of those api is much
more easy and that's again illustrating
the difference between an infrastructure
and the programming model so the
infrastructure is defined by say JMS for
example but this doesn't necessarily
mean that you have to use the official
JMS API that is probably quite hard to
use in some areas but you can add a
layer of abstraction like the Spring
Framework for example and use it even
more easily so that's something that I
would add here apart from that I would
fully agree that those features of an
application server are not challenged at
least in the Java world and are really
important to get something working in
the enterprise area ok another topic
that we should address before we finish
this one is aspects of course aspect
oriented programming is not something
that has been invented in the enterprise
area traditionally it has its roots and
meta programming and meta object
protocols which is something Gregoire
talked about in his interview but there
is also another kind of ancestry for
aspects and that is actually application
service and specifically component
containers because historically EG v
component containers have played the
role of an aspect framework with certain
predefined aspects so i mean it did
handle cross-cutting concerns security
scalability and so on so that's why
aspects are important in the enterprise
world and also if you take a look at
JBoss for example they generalize the
approach of an applications of a
container into this gave us four had
this generalized aspect container where
you could add your own interceptors so
that's why aspects are important in the
enterprise area so anything you want to
say about this topic we discussed this
topic to a large extent in the server
component patterns issue of the podcast
for me it's important to point out that
aspects are an important part of
enterprise Java certain aspects like
transactions or security were introduced
in HP and have been wrong there for
quite a long time the point is that a
generalized approach to hello P is
missing in Java EE and that has been
missing for HS I think in it should be
three there will be a primitive way of
doing AOP you could argue that softness
filters are something like AOP but this
is not the point the the real point is
to have a means of defining your own
aspects of changing the behavior of
aspects that are already there like
transactions or security
them for your own needs there are good
approaches for this that have been
worked on for like I don't know I mean
spectra is from 1997
so it's mature and has been there for a
long time and also for example the
Spring Framework offers a set of aspects
JBoss was already mentioned the JBoss
AOP framework and this is really really
an important part I believe it's
probably important to listen to the
server component patterns episode as
well because what this boils down to is
that basically intercepting chords two
components are the thing that allows you
to implement all these nice features
like transactions security instance
pooling and so on and so on I think it's
remarkable that even though this is so
important
there is no generalized idea about this
in Java EE as a whole and it's probably
the same as the generalized component
idea it's just not there Java EE there
are several different parts that somehow
look into this there is e 2 B 3 that add
some to this there is the servlet filter
approach and so on but it's not
something that is there and it's
generalized so therefore I think it's
important to have a look at a spectra
for example spring AOP or JBoss AOP and
to think about whether this can be a
help for your own applications and your
own work
ok so let's wrap up what is the state of
Java Enterprise today and where do we go
from here the important point is Java in
the enterprise is very strong it's not
going to go away for quite some time
because of the standardization of
infrastructure the big players the
strategic commitment they have and I
also think there is no real competition
for this in the enterprise I mean you
could argue that transaction monitors up
a competition COBOL is a competition
order net but Java is really really
strong there the most important point is
to distinguish between infrastructure
and programming models and to realize
that there are a lot of competiting
frameworks and programming models
available and then to use the one that
fits you best kind of best of three Pro
there and to look at the open market
there even though you are using some
open-source framework there you're not
losing the ability to let your
application run on any application
server you ever want to have for the web
frameworks there is strong competition
like Ruby on Rails and there is a lot of
innovation going on there and I think in
this field it's not quite sure how this
will end but it's really important to
point out the pure web applications that
try to put a database into the web
strictly speaking this is not even an
enterprise application because it's not
trying to solve real Enterprise issues
like integration problems and
large-scale distributed computation and
as Infernus communication and so on and
of course all those topics you mentioned
right at the end are those things that
are today done with service-oriented
architectures we're not going to go into
this one today but that's certainly
something for a future episode to
discuss as ouais with respect to Java EE
or maybe also without respect to Java EE
so I think that's it for today anything
else you want to say thanks for this
vibe thanks bye
[Music]
this was another episode of software
engineering radio the software
engineering radio team wants to thank
Henning poly for providing the music as
well as Lipson comm for hosting in
bandwidth for more information on the
podcast past episodes and feedback go to
s e - radio dotnet
[Music]